<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-02-23T15:20:22+05:30</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Aditya Bidikar — Comic Book Letterer</title><subtitle>I'm Aditya Bidikar, and I letter comics like Drifter, Motor Crush,  Black Cloud and Grant Morrison's 18 Days, as well as upcoming comics  like Femme Magnifique, Grafity's Wall and VS (full list of credits below).  Currently available for hire. Email: aditya@adityab.net. Twitter: @adityab.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Right Now Nothing Is Happening</title><link href="/blog/2019/04/11/right-now-nothing-is-happening/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Right Now Nothing Is Happening" /><published>2019-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-04-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/04/11/right-now-nothing-is-happening</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/04/11/right-now-nothing-is-happening/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This essay was originally posted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/dgFCwH&quot;&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt; dated 10 May 2017.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Religion has been on my mind, recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I turned atheist, the act of &lt;em&gt;becoming&lt;/em&gt; was separate from coming to not believe in a deity. The latter was a thought that occurred, accreted and endured, the former a protective shell of an identity that needed to be sloughed off eventually. Back then, I wouldn’t have acknowleged that people have an instinct for religion and that this might need an outlet even if the outlet isn’t necessarily religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But over time, I’ve come to think that just like an instinct for money (or at least for a substrate of exchange) and society, there is an instinct for religion. This doesn’t, obviously, mean that I endorse organised religion or even that religion &lt;em&gt;makes sense&lt;/em&gt;, but that the human animal needs to be part of something bigger in that peculiar abstracted sense which has developed into religion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve been shoring up interesting belief systems that I might want to reach for in weak moments which would still, on balance, be more acceptable to me than organised religion. I legitimately hope that there are atheists in foxholes and that I’ll be one of them, but I’d hate to not allow myself to change my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been keeping tabs on Alan Moore’s strange religion-for-one from that point of view.* You can look for details elsewhere, but, &lt;a href=&quot;http://dailygrail.com/Interviews/2017/4/Alan-Moore-Science-Imagination-Language-and-Spirits-Place&quot;&gt;from this latest interview&lt;/a&gt;, here’s a bit about how he thinks of the universe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Obviously, as a storyteller the element of time and the narrative uses to which you can put it are tremendous fun, but I think if I’ve been drawn to telling stories like this – and I certainly appear to have been – then that would be because time itself is a subject that has fascinated me since my early childhood, when studying framed photographs of deceased forebears it came to me that at some point in the future, after I was dead, people would be examining photographs of me, and that from a certain perspective this was already happening.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;As I’ve grown and have come to understand more about the position that I have learned is called Eternalism, then I’ve come to feel that it offers a vivid alternative to both ridiculously optimistic religious belief and an atheistic pessimism that is probably psychologically unworkable. I recently received a wonderful letter from someone who said that reading &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt; had helped resolve the terror of mortality that had dogged them since childhood, bringing with it debilitating anxiety and depression. This is all I ever wanted the book to achieve; the hope that it might offer a solidly rational new view of death that would provide an alternative to letting our life be morbidly overshadowed by our paralysed and fruitless fear of its end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;* I’m pretty sure El Sandifer wrote an essay about customising Moore’s ritual practices and wrapping them around William Blake’s pantheon to create a personal religion. It should be traceable somewhere on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eruditorumpress.com/&quot;&gt;Eruditorum Press website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the same subject, here’s Nick Cave from the recent film &lt;em&gt;One More Time With Feeling&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I emailed a friend last night and I was mentioning how time felt elastic these days. And he emailed me back a very excited and lovely email – where he spoke about the idea that all things were happening all the time. All past, present and future are happening now – right now. That basically a caveman was clubbing a female mate at the same time that astronauts – or scientists – were trying to work out how to colonise Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Now, that is encouraging, right? And I think he meant well, but it’s not true because … it’s not true because if everything was happening &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, I wouldn’t be sitting here waiting for the film crew to work out how to work this ridiculous 3D black-and-white camera. Right now nothing is happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repudiation is gentle but firmly dismissive. It’s the same sort of attitude I’ve had to the existence of God so far – well, it’s possible, I suppose, but it’s still an irrelevant concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But its relevance is, just like that of fiction, in the eye of the beholder. It’s relevant if it’s useful. And Cave himself gets at precisely that in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gq.com/story/the-love-and-terror-of-nick-cave&quot;&gt;the other interview&lt;/a&gt; I found myself fascinated by. To the self-proposed question ‘Do I believe in God?’, he says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a songwriter it is important for me to have a kind of belief system that can travel and change as I see fit. Orthodoxy and atheism seem to be like battery hens, stuck in the same cage, having the same old debate. Of course, my beliefs, such as they are, cannot bear up to much scrutiny and fall apart when challenged, but that is because the debate about the existence of God seems to rest on the concept of truth. As a songwriter, I am not much interested in truth, or at least truth takes a backseat to meaning and emotional resonance; meaning, not in the sense of rational meaning, but rather, meaningfulness or value. So, when I hear a song of praise sung to a God that on any empirical level probably doesn’t exist, I am somehow moved &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt;, and filled with a deep respect for that human need for meaning that is so powerful, so desperate and so beautifully absurd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this, the two seem to concur. Asked about his worship of Glycon and his meetings with mythical beings including, possibly, the demon Asmodeus, Moore says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When it comes to other conscious entities – in this current reality or any other – it is part of our condition that we can never know for sure that they are real in the sense we feel ourselves to be real. This is unfortunately true whether you’re talking to the demon Asmodeus, to a supposed Artificial Intelligence, to an LSD-provided hallucination of Yogi Bear, or to your mum.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In practical terms I personally find that the best test, whatever kind of entity we’re talking about, is to determine whether this entity is providing you with any real information, be that intellectual or emotional or, for want of a better word, spiritual. If it spouts nonsense that has no resonance or relationship with anything in your experience of reality, then it’s generally safe to regard such an entity as being in all practical terms unreal, even if it’s your mum or, say, an apparently existent President of the United States. If, on the other hand, its information seems to be coherent and has application to the world as you yourself perceive it, then it would seem only polite to interact with and address such an entity as if they were as real as you yourself, even if it’s an LSD-provided hallucination of Yogi Bear.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I think if we acknowledge that the world of matter and the world of mind are both equally ‘real’, albeit it completely different ways, then what we are left with are the above criteria. The question, rather than “is this entity real?” becomes instead “is this entity of either use or ornament?” In these terms, Glycon and all the people I met down at the homeless shelter last week are definitely real, while Boris Johnson and Barney the Dinosaur definitely aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The common thread here is that to both, the truth value of religion and belief is unimportant. It is useful as a lens through which to view things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is, in a literal way, a useful fiction, something that you pretend to take as literally true so you can then move on to talk about other things interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to Cave, at least, it’s an essential lens, considering he went through a religious phase that coincided with the height of his addicted phase. (Correlation isn’t causation, I know, but juxtaposition is a valid aesthetic choice nonetheless, on which this entire essay is predicated.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I was fucking crazy. Towards the end, I was waking up cold turkey and going to church, sick as a fucking dog. I’m sitting there sweating and listening to everything, and then trotting down … and scoring and getting back home and shooting up and going, ‘I’m living a well-rounded existence.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Moore’s case, the idea of the useful fiction reflects itself in &lt;em&gt;From Hell&lt;/em&gt;, wherein he considers a patently nonsense theory about the identity of Jack the Ripper to be utter truth, going out of his way to give it heft, and uses it to build a story about the horror of the British class system and the ugly birth of the 20th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing fiction, this is the balance you’re always struggling to strike. Everything you’re writing is false, but you would still like to &lt;em&gt;lie honestly&lt;/em&gt;.* So that when you imbue a thing with meaning, you’re doing so responsibly. After all, there’s a power to narrative. The human animal is &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; fond of patterns, and storytellers are our primary pattern-creators in both quantity and influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;* This and a couple of other thoughts to do with Alan Moore and&lt;/em&gt; From Hell &lt;em&gt;are either inspired or borrowed from the discussion in &lt;a href=&quot;http://wrongwithauthority.libsyn.com/episode-1-murder-by-decree-from-hell&quot;&gt;Wrong With Authority’s episode&lt;/a&gt; on&lt;/em&gt; From Hell &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; Murder By Decree &lt;em&gt;and I’d be remiss not to direct your attention to that excellent podcast.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, it might be useful to add a third participant to our imagined conversation. If you needed proof of how language and storytelling can bridge time and space, this one’s dead, even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s Sir Terry Pratchett on our drive for narrative and meaning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] humans seem to need to project a kind of interior decoration on to the universe, so that they spend much of the time in a world of their own making. We seem – at least at the moment – to need these things. Concepts like gods, truth and the soul appear to exist only in so far as humans consider them to do so … But they work some magic for us. They add narrativium to our culture. They bring pain, hope despair, and comfort. They wind up our elastic. Good or bad, they’ve made us into people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] Narrativium is powerful stuff. We have always had a drive to paint stories on to the Universe. When humans first looked at the stars, which are great flaming suns an unimaginable distance away, they saw in amongst them giant bulls, dragons, and local heroes. This human trait doesn’t affect what the rules say – not much, anyway – but it does determine which rules we are willing to contemplate in the first place. Moreover, the rules of the universe have to be able to produce everything that we humans observe, which introduce a kind of narrative imperative into science, too. Humans think in stories …&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of meaningless and cruel reality, it can feel, at times, a bit trite to be creating narratives. Perhaps even irresponsible. Narratives constantly shape the world. Even in public memory, the real person quickly becomes irrelevant and a narrative of them takes their place that gets enshrined as truth soon enough. And it’s fine to think of religion in terms of useful fiction when it begins to effect real damage. There’s a conflict between our innocuous drive to look for something bigger and what large groups can do in its pursuit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Some say why waste your time believing in God when there is so much natural beauty and awesomeness around us. Some say that there is more beauty and wonder looking at a butterfly and I agree, butterflies are beautiful things, but if you get a human being to look closely at a butterfly, to look very closely and get some more human beings to look at that butterfly so that there is a collective of people all peering intently at the butterfly they will ultimately fall to their knees and worship that butterfly. It’s the way humans are put together. I don’t think that makes them stupid. I think it’s kind of sweet. Until someone says well my butterfly is the true butterfly and yours is not and flies a plane into the twin towers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And even in the personal arena, I wonder how useful it is to cling on to stories. As I return to writing stories of my own, rather than only helping people tell theirs, it becomes scary how stories escape and turn into things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the death of his son, Cave muses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yeah, things have been torn apart, and I’m desperately trying to find a way of making some kind of a narrative sense out of it, if we’re talking about songwriting, or at least some sense out of it […] I can reduce this chaotic mess that’s happened down into something that’s more … distill it down into a platitude that I can fit nicely … you know a kind of greeting-card-sized platitude that means something to me, like ‘he lives in my heart’ or something like that. People say it all the time to me, he lives in my heart, and I go, yeah yeah. But he doesn’t. I mean, he’s in my heart but he doesn’t live at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] Kind of … great trauma isn’t actually a good thing [for creativity]. You know we all &lt;em&gt;wish&lt;/em&gt; we had something to write about – something in our lives that can happen, to write about and to make our lives interesting, that sort of stuff. But actually, trauma, I think, in that this happened, and the events that happened – it was extremely damaging to the creative process. The imagination needs room to move, it needs to room to invent, and to dream. And when a trauma happens that’s that big, there’s no room, there’s just no imaginative room around. There’s just the fucking trauma. And I think that was what the problem was when I tried to do new songs in the studio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a story I was trying to write about the loss of language. I’m not going to pretend it doesn’t have a lot to do with watching my father slowly lose words as his brain reduces from a worded state to an unworded one. And it’s a pretty stupid story, because I have no idea what I’m trying to tell myself with it apart from the fact that I feel sad about what’s happening (you can’t see the shape of the thing from inside it). There were many ways in which I’d thought about losing my father. This wasn’t one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Terence McKenna’s declaration of language being in superposition over the ‘real’ universe, Moore says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[It] is no more than the truth to point out that language separates us from the probably psychedelic pre-verbal reality that we enjoyed as infants. What is also true, of course, is that if the infant individual (or infant culture) does not acquire language, then they will find themselves at something of a disadvantage when it comes to surviving in the physical world: in short, they very probably won’t. What I’m saying is that the acquisition of language seems to involve a necessary trade off in terms of our direct experience of the world versus our ability to function in that world. This is our human situation, and the way to make the best of it is to utilise language to its fullest and most spectacular extent. No, it won’t reconnect us to the universe in the way that we were connected as infants – this is possibly what psychedelic drugs are for – but I would suggest we take a look at what medium Terence McKenna chose to beautifully express the loss of our speechless Eden before we come to personify language as some form of neurological tyrant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you can’t see the shape of the thing from inside it, are you ever really in a position to be objective, ever? Are you ever outside your own life? How do we even understand whether an objective reality exists or not if we’re all looking from within our subjective selves?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;All of this stuff that I’m saying now, it feels like it’s just a load of bullshit to me. It may mean something, but in the end, there’s something that happened, and there’s a kind of ring around that event – it’s fenced off – and everything else is okay around it, but there’s just something that happened in that short space of time that we can never get that far away from. … There was something – I was rattling on about time being elastic – I think that’s what I meant, that we’re attached to this event. That we move away like we’re on a rubberband, and life can go on and on and on. But eventually it keeps coming back to that thing. That’s some kind of trauma, I guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We consistently overlay meaning on our past retroactively to fit the present. The present is constantly eschatological in nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Looking back over the last twenty years, a certain clarity prevails. Amidst the madness and the mayhem, it would seem I have been banging on one particular drum. I see that my artistic life has centred around an attempt to articulate an almost palpable sense of loss which laid claim to my life. A great gaping hole was blasted out of my world by the unexpected death of my father…. The way I learned to fill this hole, this void, was to write. […] I always thought the traumatic incident was the death of my father, but actually I don’t think the traumatic experience had actually happened. It was waiting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even at the moment of declaring the falsity of the overriding narrative of his creative life, Nick reaches towards the sad, pretty sentiment of a different narrative – it wasn’t Nick the son to his father that was the character he was playing, it was Nick the father to his son that he was waiting to play:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My consciousness exists only at this given time. It has no past, and no future. But its present is bigger in magnitude than all the trillion stars and planets and galaxies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This essay was originally posted in my newsletter dated 10 May 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Photograph of You</title><link href="/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Photograph of You" /><published>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This short story was originally posted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/dgFCwH&quot;&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt; dated 7 July 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a photograph I have of you. There’s you, and two boys. The three of you sitting crosslegged against a brick wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re twenty-one in this picture, which I know because the three of us went on holiday to bring in your birthday, and this is the morning after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a cold morning, I can tell. You’re wearing a dark woollen cap and a shawl your mum gave you draped over your shoulders. Your toes peek out under the corners of the shawl, which you’ve clearly just thrown on because it seems to have drifted open, revealing the thin, translucent kurta you liked to sleep in back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your head is thrown back in laughter, your nostrils open like a horse’s. The way you do that, I’ve told you sometimes, it’s like I can see all the way to your brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re laughing, you’re leaning against one of the boys. The one that’s not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s bent forward, his head down at his knees, so your cheek is against his back. His hands reflexively smooth back his hair – a habit you and I find incredibly self-conscious but which he cannot or will not stop. I can’t see his face in the photo, but clearly he’s bent over laughing. The two of you, laughing together, leaning on each other. He’s wearing a sweater over the sort of long shorts that used to be popular when you were twenty-one. These days, he’ll swear that he always knew they looked stupid, but that’s a lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photo’s in black-and-white, so it’s not reasonable for my memory to tell me that the brick wall was red, that your woollen cap was dark blue, or that the morning fog is why the photo looks slightly faded, or even that the little white flash I can see on your upturned face is not lens flare but the nose-ring you stopped wearing two years later even though you knew I liked it. Memory could be deceptive – a brick wall might just look red to me the way it looks in my head rather than the hundred subtle shades of yellow, orange, and wounded blue it probably had from being baked by hundreds of different people in different kilns for different lengths of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In black-and-white, the whole thing looks a little staged. I remember photos from my parents’ wedding, and from later, when I was a kid, when the idea of candid photography was a bit strange, and everyone in a photograph always looked stiffer than they meant to. Colour is the present, while the past is artificially posed puppetry. You caught mid-action, raising one hand to your mouth, him seemingly about to bang his head on the ground (he wasn’t – that’s just how he laughed), your other hand slipping from the hold the boy on the other side of you had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boy on the other side of you, that’s me. I’m sitting there wearing your t-shirt from the day before, with little boxer shorts underneath. You find it weird how I don’t feel cold ‘like normal people’, but the fact is I enjoy the way my skin bursts out in goosebumps when it gets just slightly colder than I can easily tolerate. The anticipation of that involuntary shiver my body gives to generate heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking at you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the only one lounging against the wall. I’m blowing out smoke from the cigarette I’m holding in one hand. I’m trying to look cool, but I look like someone too old to be amusing himself with the shapes his cold breath creates in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few moments, I’ll pass the cigarette on to you, and you’ll give me a side-eyed look. Sometimes the look was indulgent, as if you liked checking if I was there – like I was your domain and you were surveying it and seeing it was good. But sometimes it meant you wanted to tell me you were on to me, it meant you’d noticed something I was trying to hide and failing, and that you’d talk to me about it later. I don’t remember which one it was, but I remember the look. In any case, it’s not in the photograph. It’ll happen in the moment after the click, and it’ll be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your hand in mine is still there in the photo. I can see it. You’re drawing your hand away from mine, because you have a habit of covering your mouth with both hands when you think you’re laughing too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is, once again, not in the photograph is the fact that I’ll resist. I won’t let your hand go from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll pause in your laughter and look at me quizzically. There’ll be something in your look, a bit haunted – I won’t say a thing, just not let go. You’ll be nonplussed, and I won’t be able to tell you what I’m thinking. Then slowly, your eyes holding mine to task, you’ll pull away. Finger by finger, your hand will slip from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few seconds, I’ll smile and pass you the cigarette, but before that, there’ll just be your pinky finger hooked into mine. You’ll hold it there for a moment, but then, you’ll shake your head, and you’ll disengage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This short story was originally posted in my newsletter dated 7 July 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assassinistas</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assassinistas" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Tini Howard, Gilbert Hernandez, Rob Davis and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; The lettering style for &lt;em&gt;Assassinistas&lt;/em&gt; is inspired by Gilbert Hernandez’s own hand-lettering, which I’m a big fan of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Tini Howard, Gilbert Hernandez, Rob Davis and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Black Cloud</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Black Cloud" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Iván Brandon, Jason Latour, Greg Hinkle, Matt Wilson and Tom Muller, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC01_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC01_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC02_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #2&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC03_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #3&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Iván Brandon, Jason Latour, Greg Hinkle, Matt Wilson and Tom Muller, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking the Rules</title><link href="/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking the Rules" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally written for PanelxPanel magazine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, you won’t know if you don’t try, will you?”—that’s the one thing I remember from the email exchange, seven years ago, that led to my first professional lettering project. Specifically, it was said to me by my publisher in response to my telling him that I lettered a bit, just for fun, but I didn’t think I could do it professionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to carry that in my mind, especially since I decided I would make a career in comics while working from India, where the comics industry lies in sub-zero temperatures, a twitching near-corpse. To be clear, I have had extraordinary good luck in terms of employers and collaborators (two of whom come from similar circumstances and talk about them above this little bit), but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of the journey so far has simply been to listen to prescriptions and to doggedly ignore them—you can’t make money in comics in India, everybody wants to hire someone in their geographical vicinity, you will only ever be seen as somebody to outsource cheap work to, you gotta know people to get ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically that last one has been the most hollow, because the single biggest reason I have any work right now is that I asked strangers to look at my work and they responded with kindness they had no reason or obligation to display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to carry this into the work itself, especially with my contention that the received wisdom about comics lettering—“Good lettering is invisible”—is bullshit. I sincerely mean this, but apart from that, it’s just useful to think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your opinion about your craft will define the contours of the work you produce, and I fail to see how aspiring to be unremarkable is of any use to producing good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witness &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;, where my collaborators and I have been attempting to put our money where our mouth is. Working around the script, I habitually add little touches like taking a panel where the reader doesn’t hear speech and reinforcing that idea by adding squiggles, implying speech, or responding to Dev’s turning a panel on its side by rotating the balloon likewise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continued to work on the project, Ram noticed and enjoyed these things I added, and, in issue 3, decided to build an entire section around the lettering, to the extent that he and I laid out the pages for that section and marked out panels for Dev (who, to his immense credit, responded with enthusiasm rather than with annoyance) to then draw. The lettering for these sections was then baked into the artwork and sent over to our colourist Dearbhla who added her magic. All because we looked at the rule—“Good lettering should be invisible”—and went, “Sez who?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/img/Paradiso3_Spread.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paradiso #3&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt; #3&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written extensively about this elsewhere, but part of producing interesting work is feeling ownership of what you’re doing. If you trust your collaborators, you can be assured they will let you know when you’re going too wild, where you need to rein yourself in, but even if you face the occasional embarrassment of failing in public, at least there remains a chance of you producing something genuinely interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Originally written for PanelxPanel magazine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grafity’s Wall</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grafity’s Wall" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Ram V, Anand Radhakrishnan, Irma Kniivila and Jason Wordie, published by Unbound Books.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; As Ram is fond of reminding me, hand-lettering &lt;em&gt;Grafity’s Wall&lt;/em&gt; was a decision I made in a pub while out drinking with him and Anand, and it ended up a tremendous learning experience. After figuring out a good lettering style and workflow (documented in detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://unbound.com/books/grafitys-wall/updates/writing-between-the-lines&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I lettered the whole thing on paper over printouts of Anand’s line art and matched it back to the final pages digitally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_66.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_74.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_90.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Ram V, Anand Radhakrishnan, Irma Kniivila and Jason Wordie, published by Unbound Books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Isola</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/isola/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Isola" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/isola</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/isola/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Brenden Fletcher, Karl Kerschl and MSassyK, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; I was asked to letter &lt;em&gt;Isola&lt;/em&gt; after working with Brenden on &lt;em&gt;Motor Crush&lt;/em&gt;. I worked from Karl’s rough lettering to figure out a style with hand-drawn borderless balloons, and create sound effects that worked with the “language” he created for the sounds, most of which he letters himself. I also created an alphabet/script for the Moro language that is used from issue 3 onwards. I was interviewed about the process of lettering &lt;em&gt;Isola&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.comics-now.com/home/2018/4/2/lettering-a-legend-aditya-bidikar-on-the-highly-collaborative-isola&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola03_21.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #3&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Brenden Fletcher, Karl Kerschl and MSassyK, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Little Bird</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Little Bird" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Darcy van Poelgeest, Ian Bertram, Matt Hollingsworth and Ben Didier, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Little Bird&lt;/em&gt; uses my custom font ‘Mighty Mouse’ for the body copy, along with a rough, energetic ballooning style that lets me insert hand-drawn lettering alongside the fonts, so I can move from more consistent lettering for the quieter scenes to more varied balloons and sound effects for the dynamic action scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Darcy van Poelgeest, Ian Bertram, Matt Hollingsworth and Ben Didier, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Punks Not Dead</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Punks Not Dead" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with David Barnett, Martin Simmonds, Dee Cunniffe and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Punks Not Dead&lt;/em&gt; was the debut book for my font ‘Sitting Duck’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND01_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND01_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND04_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND04_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with David Barnett, Martin Simmonds, Dee Cunniffe and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slicing a Story</title><link href="/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slicing a Story" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reposted from the previous version of this blog. Thought this was useful enough to keep around.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a scene change in a novel. The transition between, usually, one chapter and the next. There is a gap in between, wherein the writer shifts time (usually going forward) and place, and possibly characters. Usually, this gap contains the irrelevant bits, the bits that are excised to make a story readable. Sometimes, this gap may contain relevant information, but mostly the writer brings you up to speed as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is slicing the story. There are pieces created and kept next to each other, and the writer tries to make you not notice when you skip across these gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These gaps are essential. Not all information is necessary or relevant, and it would be tedious if you followed characters through, say, a long, silent car ride for no reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an expansion of the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; basic level of gap, the one created by, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She got up from the sofa, reached the door, and let the dog in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re skipping the fact that she &lt;em&gt;walked from the sofa to the door&lt;/em&gt;, and that she &lt;em&gt;opened the door&lt;/em&gt;. The reader fills in these gaps without needing to be told, because they’ve been trained through the act of reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens all the time in comics. The space between each panel and the next is a gap which is filled in by the reader. Scott McCloud calls this closure. It ranges from the basic (&lt;em&gt;a.&lt;/em&gt; the doorbell rings while I’m on the sofa, &lt;em&gt;b.&lt;/em&gt; I have opened the door) to the quite complex in the hands of an ambitious writer (see something like &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; or much of what Grant Morrison does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a comic, additionally, scene changes tend to look exactly the same as panel changes - they are both a gap between two panels - and the reader has to make the deduction that the action has moved, an example of how comics (as we might talk about at some point) can entice the reader into making the effort to close very large gaps by making them look like small ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to prose, in the basic storytelling model (where style is supposed to be invisible), the writer tries to require a minimal amount of closure from the reader. All relevant information is contained on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the writing maxim ‘come in late, leave early’ is being followed, the gap is larger, and the writer has to work hard to make the reader commit a greater act of closure without noticing that’s what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, a writer could lean into it. Slice the story in a way that the reader notices it’s being sliced. This creates the basis for non-linear storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple version of this can be seen in many of Stephen King’s books (for example, &lt;em&gt;The Stand&lt;/em&gt;). The writer skips between different characters without skipping around in time too much, and when they come back to a particular strand, time has passed, stuff has happened, which is explained as the story moves along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly more evolved version of this can be seen in George R. R. Martin’s &lt;em&gt;Ice and Fire&lt;/em&gt; series, where each character’s story progresses in a linear manner &lt;em&gt;in itself&lt;/em&gt;, but skipping between strands involves jumping into the past and future. To make this clear: Chapter 7 involving Character A might be taking place months &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 8 involving Character B. The amount of information being exchanged between two strands, however, is minimal, as guaranteed by the lack of communications technology on Westeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But lean even further into it, and you reach what is generally called non-linear storytelling. Stay with the character, but skip back and forth in time. (See &lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse-Five&lt;/em&gt; and its descendants.) So information conveyed in Chapter 7 will give the reader an extra weapon to interpret the information conveyed in Chapter 8 which chronologically takes place &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used by a smart writer, this can be built on to provide two progressions, one chronological and the other thematic - one the story-internal order in which events occur, and the other the order in which events have been presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, if I’m reading Chapter 8, not only am I using information conveyed about the past and the future of these events, I also close the gap between Chapter 7 and Chapter 8 by interpreting why these two chapters having been placed next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if this is used in conjunction with multiple characters and multiple strands, I’m also creating a thematic (or maybe even purely story-based) dialogue between the scenes based on the chosen juxtaposition (as seen in, say, movies like &lt;em&gt;The Prestige&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so obvious, but I thought writing it down might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Reposted from the previous version of this blog. Thought this was useful enough to keep around.</summary></entry></feed>