<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-11T10:40:01+05:30</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Aditya Bidikar — Comic Book Letterer</title><subtitle>I'm Aditya Bidikar, and I letter comics like Drifter, Motor Crush,  Black Cloud and Grant Morrison's 18 Days, as well as upcoming comics  like Femme Magnifique, Grafity's Wall and VS (full list of credits below).  Currently available for hire. Email: aditya@adityab.net. Twitter: @adityab.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Photograph of You</title><link href="/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Photograph of You" /><published>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/02/10/a-photograph-of-you/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This short story was originally posted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://eepurl.com/dgFCwH&quot;&gt;my newsletter&lt;/a&gt; dated 7 July 2018.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a photograph I have of you. There’s you, and two boys. The three of you sitting crosslegged against a brick wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re twenty-one in this picture, which I know because the three of us went on holiday to bring in your birthday, and this is the morning after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a cold morning, I can tell. You’re wearing a dark woollen cap and a shawl your mum gave you draped over your shoulders. Your toes peek out under the corners of the shawl, which you’ve clearly just thrown on because it seems to have drifted open, revealing the thin, translucent kurta you liked to sleep in back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your head is thrown back in laughter, your nostrils open like a horse’s. The way you do that, I’ve told you sometimes, it’s like I can see all the way to your brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While you’re laughing, you’re leaning against one of the boys. The one that’s not me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He’s bent forward, his head down at his knees, so your cheek is against his back. His hands reflexively smooth back his hair—a habit you and I find incredibly self-conscious but which he cannot or will not stop. I can’t see his face in the photo, but clearly he’s bent over laughing. The two of you, laughing together, leaning on each other. He’s wearing a sweater over the sort of long shorts that used to be popular when you were twenty-one. These days, he’ll swear that he always knew they looked stupid, but that’s a lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photo’s in black-and-white, so it’s not reasonable for my memory to tell me that the brick wall was red, that your woollen cap was dark blue, or that the morning fog is why the photo looks slightly faded, or even that the little white flash I can see on your upturned face is not lens flare but the nose-ring you stopped wearing two years later even though you knew I liked it. Memory could be deceptive—a brick wall might just look red to me the way it looks in my head rather than the hundred subtle shades of yellow, orange, and wounded blue it probably had from being baked by hundreds of different people in different kilns for different lengths of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In black-and-white, the whole thing looks a little staged. I remember photos from my parents’ wedding, and from later, when I was a kid, when the idea of candid photography was a bit strange, and everyone in a photograph always looked stiffer than they meant to. Colour is the present, while the past is artificially posed puppetry. You caught mid-action, raising one hand to your mouth, him seemingly about to bang his head on the ground (he wasn’t—that’s just how he laughed), your other hand slipping from the hold the boy on the other side of you had on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The boy on the other side of you, that’s me. I’m sitting there wearing your t-shirt from the day before, with little boxer shorts underneath. You find it weird how I don’t feel cold ‘like normal people’, but the fact is I enjoy the way my skin bursts out in goosebumps when it gets just slightly colder than I can easily tolerate. The anticipation of that involuntary shiver my body gives to generate heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking at you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m the only one lounging against the wall. I’m blowing out smoke from the cigarette I’m holding in one hand. I’m trying to look cool, but I look like someone too old to be amusing himself with the shapes his cold breath creates in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few moments, I’ll pass the cigarette on to you, and you’ll give me a side-eyed look. Sometimes the look was indulgent, as if you liked checking if I was there—like I was your domain and you were surveying it and seeing it was good. But sometimes it meant you wanted to tell me you were on to me, it meant you’d noticed something I was trying to hide and failing, and that you’d talk to me about it later. I don’t remember which one it was, but I remember the look. In any case, it’s not in the photograph. It’ll happen in the moment after the click, and it’ll be lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your hand in mine is still there in the photo. I can see it. You’re drawing your hand away from mine, because you have a habit of covering your mouth with both hands when you think you’re laughing too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is, once again, not in the photograph is the fact that I’ll resist. I won’t let your hand go from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll pause in your laughter and look at me quizzically. There’ll be something in your look, a bit haunted—I won’t say a thing, just not let go. You’ll be nonplussed, and I won’t be able to tell you what I’m thinking. Then slowly, your eyes holding mine to task, you’ll pull away. Finger by finger, your hand will slip from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a few seconds, I’ll smile and pass you the cigarette, but before that, there’ll just be your pinky finger hooked into mine. You’ll hold it there for a moment, but then, you’ll shake your head, and you’ll disengage.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">This short story was originally posted in my newsletter dated 7 July 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Assassinistas</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Assassinistas" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/assassinistas/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Tini Howard, Gilbert Hernandez, Rob Davis and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; The lettering style for &lt;em&gt;Assassinistas&lt;/em&gt; is inspired by Gilbert Hernandez’s own hand-lettering, which I’m a big fan of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_03.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Assassinistas01_17.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; title=&quot;Assassinistas #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Tini Howard, Gilbert Hernandez, Rob Davis and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Black Cloud</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Black Cloud" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/black-cloud/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Iván Brandon, Jason Latour, Greg Hinkle, Matt Wilson and Tom Muller, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC01_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC01_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC02_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #2&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/BC03_14.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Black Cloud #3&quot; title=&quot;Black Cloud #3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Iván Brandon, Jason Latour, Greg Hinkle, Matt Wilson and Tom Muller, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking the Rules</title><link href="/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking the Rules" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/01/10/breaking-the-rules/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally written for PanelxPanel magazine.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Well, you won’t know if you don’t try, will you?”—that’s the one thing I remember from the email exchange, seven years ago, that led to my first professional lettering project. Specifically, it was said to me by my publisher in response to my telling him that I lettered a bit, just for fun, but I didn’t think I could do it professionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to carry that in my mind, especially since I decided I would make a career in comics while working from India, where the comics industry lies in sub-zero temperatures, a twitching near-corpse. To be clear, I have had extraordinary good luck in terms of employers and collaborators (two of whom come from similar circumstances and talk about them above this little bit), but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large part of the journey so far has simply been to listen to prescriptions and to doggedly ignore them—you can’t make money in comics in India, everybody wants to hire someone in their geographical vicinity, you will only ever be seen as somebody to outsource cheap work to, you gotta know people to get ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically that last one has been the most hollow, because the single biggest reason I have any work right now is that I asked strangers to look at my work and they responded with kindness they had no reason or obligation to display.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to carry this into the work itself, especially with my contention that the received wisdom about comics lettering—“Good lettering is invisible”—is bullshit. I sincerely mean this, but apart from that, it’s just useful to think so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your opinion about your craft will define the contours of the work you produce, and I fail to see how aspiring to be unremarkable is of any use to producing good work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Witness &lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt;, where my collaborators and I have been attempting to put our money where our mouth is. Working around the script, I habitually add little touches like taking a panel where the reader doesn’t hear speech and reinforcing that idea by adding squiggles, implying speech, or responding to Dev’s turning a panel on its side by rotating the balloon likewise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continued to work on the project, Ram noticed and enjoyed these things I added, and, in issue 3, decided to build an entire section around the lettering, to the extent that he and I laid out the pages for that section and marked out panels for Dev (who, to his immense credit, responded with enthusiasm rather than with annoyance) to then draw. The lettering for these sections was then baked into the artwork and sent over to our colourist Dearbhla who added her magic. All because we looked at the rule—“Good lettering should be invisible”—and went, “Sez who?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/img/Paradiso3_Spread.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Paradiso #3&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paradiso&lt;/em&gt; #3&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written extensively about this elsewhere, but part of producing interesting work is feeling ownership of what you’re doing. If you trust your collaborators, you can be assured they will let you know when you’re going too wild, where you need to rein yourself in, but even if you face the occasional embarrassment of failing in public, at least there remains a chance of you producing something genuinely interesting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Originally written for PanelxPanel magazine.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Grafity’s Wall</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Grafity’s Wall" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/grafitys-wall/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Ram V, Anand Radhakrishnan, Irma Kniivila and Jason Wordie, published by Unbound Books.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; As Ram is fond of reminding me, hand-lettering &lt;em&gt;Grafity’s Wall&lt;/em&gt; was a decision I made in a pub while out drinking with him and Anand, and it ended up a tremendous learning experience. After figuring out a good lettering style and workflow (documented in detail &lt;a href=&quot;https://unbound.com/books/grafitys-wall/updates/writing-between-the-lines&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), I lettered the whole thing on paper over printouts of Anand’s line art and matched it back to the final pages digitally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_66.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_74.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Grafity_90.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; title=&quot;Grafity's Wall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Ram V, Anand Radhakrishnan, Irma Kniivila and Jason Wordie, published by Unbound Books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Isola</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/isola/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Isola" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/isola</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/isola/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Brenden Fletcher, Karl Kerschl and MSassyK, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; I was asked to letter &lt;em&gt;Isola&lt;/em&gt; after working with Brenden on &lt;em&gt;Motor Crush&lt;/em&gt;. I worked from Karl’s rough lettering to figure out a style with hand-drawn borderless balloons, and create sound effects that worked with the “language” he created for the sounds, most of which he letters himself. I also created an alphabet/script for the Moro language that is used from issue 3 onwards. I was interviewed about the process of lettering &lt;em&gt;Isola&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.comics-now.com/home/2018/4/2/lettering-a-legend-aditya-bidikar-on-the-highly-collaborative-isola&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_05.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_10.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola01_11.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #1&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/Isola03_21.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Isola #3&quot; title=&quot;Motor Crush #6&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Brenden Fletcher, Karl Kerschl and MSassyK, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Little Bird</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Little Bird" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/little-bird/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Darcy van Poelgeest, Ian Bertram, Matt Hollingsworth and Ben Didier, published by Image Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Little Bird&lt;/em&gt; uses my custom font ‘Mighty Mouse’ for the body copy, along with a rough, energetic ballooning style that lets me insert hand-drawn lettering alongside the fonts, so I can move from more consistent lettering for the quieter scenes to more varied balloons and sound effects for the dynamic action scenes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_06.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/LittleBird01_08.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; title=&quot;Little Bird #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Darcy van Poelgeest, Ian Bertram, Matt Hollingsworth and Ben Didier, published by Image Comics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Punks Not Dead</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Punks Not Dead" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/punks-not-dead/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with David Barnett, Martin Simmonds, Dee Cunniffe and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Punks Not Dead&lt;/em&gt; was the debut book for my font ‘Sitting Duck’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND01_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND01_07.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND04_01.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/PND04_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; title=&quot;Punks Not Dead #4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with David Barnett, Martin Simmonds, Dee Cunniffe and Shelly Bond, published by Black Crown.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Slicing a Story</title><link href="/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Slicing a Story" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/2019/01/10/slicing-a-story/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reposted from the previous version of this blog. Thought this was useful enough to keep around.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a scene change in a novel. The transition between, usually, one chapter and the next. There is a gap in between, wherein the writer shifts time (usually going forward) and place, and possibly characters. Usually, this gap contains the irrelevant bits, the bits that are excised to make a story readable. Sometimes, this gap may contain relevant information, but mostly the writer brings you up to speed as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is slicing the story. There are pieces created and kept next to each other, and the writer tries to make you not notice when you skip across these gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These gaps are essential. Not all information is necessary or relevant, and it would be tedious if you followed characters through, say, a long, silent car ride for no reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an expansion of the &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; basic level of gap, the one created by, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;She got up from the sofa, reached the door, and let the dog in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re skipping the fact that she &lt;em&gt;walked from the sofa to the door&lt;/em&gt;, and that she &lt;em&gt;opened the door&lt;/em&gt;. The reader fills in these gaps without needing to be told, because they’ve been trained through the act of reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens all the time in comics. The space between each panel and the next is a gap which is filled in by the reader. Scott McCloud calls this closure. It ranges from the basic (&lt;em&gt;a.&lt;/em&gt; the doorbell rings while I’m on the sofa, &lt;em&gt;b.&lt;/em&gt; I have opened the door) to the quite complex in the hands of an ambitious writer (see something like &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; or much of what Grant Morrison does).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a comic, additionally, scene changes tend to look exactly the same as panel changes - they are both a gap between two panels - and the reader has to make the deduction that the action has moved, an example of how comics (as we might talk about at some point) can entice the reader into making the effort to close very large gaps by making them look like small ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming back to prose, in the basic storytelling model (where style is supposed to be invisible), the writer tries to require a minimal amount of closure from the reader. All relevant information is contained on the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the writing maxim ‘come in late, leave early’ is being followed, the gap is larger, and the writer has to work hard to make the reader commit a greater act of closure without noticing that’s what they’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, a writer could lean into it. Slice the story in a way that the reader notices it’s being sliced. This creates the basis for non-linear storytelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple version of this can be seen in many of Stephen King’s books (for example, &lt;em&gt;The Stand&lt;/em&gt;). The writer skips between different characters without skipping around in time too much, and when they come back to a particular strand, time has passed, stuff has happened, which is explained as the story moves along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slightly more evolved version of this can be seen in George R. R. Martin’s &lt;em&gt;Ice and Fire&lt;/em&gt; series, where each character’s story progresses in a linear manner &lt;em&gt;in itself&lt;/em&gt;, but skipping between strands involves jumping into the past and future. To make this clear: Chapter 7 involving Character A might be taking place months &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 8 involving Character B. The amount of information being exchanged between two strands, however, is minimal, as guaranteed by the lack of communications technology on Westeros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But lean even further into it, and you reach what is generally called non-linear storytelling. Stay with the character, but skip back and forth in time. (See &lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse-Five&lt;/em&gt; and its descendants.) So information conveyed in Chapter 7 will give the reader an extra weapon to interpret the information conveyed in Chapter 8 which chronologically takes place &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; Chapter 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used by a smart writer, this can be built on to provide two progressions, one chronological and the other thematic - one the story-internal order in which events occur, and the other the order in which events have been presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, if I’m reading Chapter 8, not only am I using information conveyed about the past and the future of these events, I also close the gap between Chapter 7 and Chapter 8 by interpreting why these two chapters having been placed next to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if this is used in conjunction with multiple characters and multiple strands, I’m also creating a thematic (or maybe even purely story-based) dialogue between the scenes based on the chosen juxtaposition (as seen in, say, movies like &lt;em&gt;The Prestige&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, so obvious, but I thought writing it down might be useful.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog" /><summary type="html">Reposted from the previous version of this blog. Thought this was useful enough to keep around.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">These Savage Shores</title><link href="/lettering/2019/01/10/these-savage-shores/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="These Savage Shores" /><published>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-01-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/lettering/2019/01/10/these-savage-shores</id><content type="html" xml:base="/lettering/2019/01/10/these-savage-shores/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;with Ram V, Sumit Kumar and Vittorio Astone, published by Vault Comics.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;These Savage Shores&lt;/em&gt;, while being set in the 18th century, is a very modern book, in its conception and execution. So for this book, I decided to put aside complete historical accuracy (in such things as the style of the letters being written by the characters, and documents produced from the age) and try to convey the feel of the era while retaining a unifying style with the artwork and colours. My focus was to maintain readability and to imply the era in a way that the reader could make their own connections. I also created the typeface used by Bishan in his letters back home in issue 3, inspired by uncial lettering and the Malayalam script.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/TSS01_04.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;These Savage Shores #1&quot; title=&quot;These Savage Shores #1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/TSS02_02.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;These Savage Shores #2&quot; title=&quot;These Savage Shores #2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/TSS03_18.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;These Savage Shores #3&quot; title=&quot;These Savage Shores #3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/portfolio/TSS03_22.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;These Savage Shores #3&quot; title=&quot;These Savage Shores #3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="lettering" /><summary type="html">with Ram V, Sumit Kumar and Vittorio Astone, published by Vault Comics.</summary></entry></feed>